<div class="m-portlet__body">
<!--begin::Section-->
<div class="m-scrollable mCustomScrollbar _mCS_5 mCS-autoHide" data-scrollbar-shown="true" data-scrollable="true" data-max-height="650">
<div class="m-accordion m-accordion--bordered" id="m_accordion_2" role="tablist">   
 <!--begin::Item-->

<div class="m-accordion__item">
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12861_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-icon">
<i class="fa fa-question-circle"></i>
</span>
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Do I need to buy an extra book for the preparation of exams?
<span class="m-accordion__item-mode"></span>
</div>
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12861_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
<div class="m-accordion__item-content">
<p style="word-break:break-word;">
Video lectures are sufficient to pass this course with good grades. However, you are recommended to buy books only if you think video lectures and handouts are insufficient. The names of 10 books are mentioned at your LMS.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12862_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How should I prepare for my quizzes and assignments?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12862_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
For better results in quizzes and assignments, watch every video lecture. Make sure you don’t leave any important details.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12863_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Can I retake the quiz?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12863_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
No, Department of Pakistan Studies has no re-take policy regarding any activity of this course.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12870_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How is the percentage of this course divided among activities?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12870_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The mid term exam will carry 25% percentage&nbsp;while final term exam carry 60% percentage of your total grade. While 15% percentage is for other course related activities i.e. quizzes and GDB.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12872_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is GDB?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12872_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
GDB (Graded Discussion Board) is an activity in which you are given a current affair question and you have to give your opinion.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12873_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the exam pattern of this course?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12873_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Exams are usually consists of MCQs and short questions of 2, 3 and 5 marks. However, paper is subjected to change and you’ll be informed via course announcement before exams.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12874_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">I have watched the full lecture but the 'Green Tick' isn't visible. What should I do?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12874_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
If you are facing the problems such as not appearing green tick, not opening of video, not opening of next tab or difficulty in performing the course activities through VU-LMS then you are advised to&nbsp;don’t post&nbsp;your queries on&nbsp;MDB.&nbsp;In such a case, you should put your Ticket/ Query&nbsp;with proper screenshots&nbsp;to&nbsp;the&nbsp;IT Department&nbsp;in this regard through&nbsp;VU Support System.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12854_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the medium of instruction in the Pak301 course?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12854_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Medium of instruction is only English in Virtual University of Pakistan. Urdu or Roman Urdu is not allowed for any activity of this course including Quiz, GDB, Assignment and Mid &amp; Final-term examination.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12855_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is meant by Separate Electorates?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12855_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Separate Electorates are type of elections in which minorities select their own representatives separately, as opposed to Joint Electorates where people are selected collectively. When minorities fear that they would not get representation in state affairs and government then they demand separate electorates. Same was the case with the Indian Muslims. They were very large in number, but in case of combined elections they would not get due representation. When the British implemented the system of democracy in India in order to strength their rule, and to involve local people in government, the Muslims demanded separate electorates. These were not imposed by British, however were granted on the request of the Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#12856_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Explain the terms ‘Legitimize and delegitimize’.
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="12856_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Legitimize
To legitimize something that means to officially approve it, or make it seem acceptable.
Delegitimize
To make something illegal that was previously legal
It demonstrates that nationalism, as a collective consciousness, is embedded in the very system of colonialism that it apparently was confronting and trying to delegitimize.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#9363_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is J.S.C?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="9363_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
J.S.C stands for Joint Select Committee that was formed by British Parliament in 1933 for Indian constitutional reforms.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#8616_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is democracy?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="8616_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Democracy is the most powerful form of government and it is the fundamental and distinctive character of modern age. It has also been regarded as the most favorable and decisive form of government which requires active participation of the people in the decision making process, because without public collaboration, democracy could not flourish properly. According to Abraham Lincoln, “Democracy is a form of government for the people, by the people and through the people”.
Democracy has three basic senses in contemporary usage: (1) a form of government in which the right to make political decisions is exercised directly by the whole body of citizens, acting under procedures of majority rule, usually known as direct democracy; (2) a form of government in which the citizens exercise the same right not in person but through representatives chosen by and responsible to them, known as representative democracy; and (3) a form of government, usually a representative democracy, in which the powers of the majority are exercised within a frame work of constitutional restraints designed to guarantee all citizens the enjoyment of certain individual or collective rights, such as freedom of speech and religion, known as liberal, or constitutional, democracy."
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7926_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between Martial Law and Military Rule?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7926_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Martial law can be defined as the imposition of military power in the country for temporary bases. Martial law is imposed when the civilian government or civilian authorities fail to function properly, when there are extensive riots and protests, or when the disobedience of the law becomes widespread. Typically, the imposition of martial law accompanies curfews, the suspension of civil law, civil rights, habeas corpus, and the application or extension of military law or military justice to civilians. Civilians defying martial law may be subjected to military tribunals because courts become dysfunctional during martial law. The Constitution is suspended and fundamental rights are usurped during martial law and the law enforcing agencies report to the military officers during martial law.
Military rule is the one where a country’s administration and the implementation of its law and order are under the control of the military. Military rule takes the form of military dictatorship, a junta or a military structure. Most of the military governments end up being oppressive regimes. Military regime led by General Pervez Musharraf has been described as the military rule because the civil laws and fundamental rights were not usurped by the state under Musharraf and the civil courts and constitution were also functional. He, being the head of the military, overlooked and supervised the state affairs. He after some time established a puppet democratic set up in the country but the ultimate power was in the hands of the military.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7670_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What do you know about the Government of India Act, 1935?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7670_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The deliberations of the round table conference resulted in the Government of India Act 1935. 
The main features of the Act were: 
1. A Federation of India was promised for, comprising both provinces and states. The provisions of the Act establishing the federal central government were not to go into operation until a specified number of rulers of states had signed Instruments of Accession. Since, this did not happen, the central government continued to function in accordance with the 1919 Act and only the part of the 1935 Act dealing with the provincial governments went into operation. 
2. The provinces were given autonomy with respect to subjects delegated to them. 
3. Dyarchy came to an end, and the provincial governments now had full responsibility. 
4. Sind was made a separate province. 
5. Separate electorates were continued. 
6. One third Muslim representation in the Central Legislature was guaranteed. 
7. Autonomous provincial governments in eleven provinces under ministries responsible to legislatures would be setup. 
The Act came into force on April 1, 1937.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7667_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the Nationalization of 1970,s?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7667_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In the early 1970s nationalization was a very popular theme in developing countries. In the name of social justice, socialism and for the promotion of equality not only in Pakistan but in most of the developing countries nationalization was adopted as a political and economic strategy. In Pakistan a number of steps were taken by the Z. A. Bhutto government to pursue the nationalization policy. Several key industries which were owned by private groups were taken over by the state of Pakistan under a martial law order on January 2, 1972. These industries included iron and steel, basic metals, heavy engineering, heavy electrical, motor vehicle and tractor production, heavy basic chemicals, petro chemicals, cement, gas and oil refinery. Emerald mines in Swat, life insurance, schools, colleges and banks were also nationalized in 1974. All these steps were taken under the rubric of nationalization.
These industries were the core of the economy at that time and were taken over by the state from the private groups. Nationalization policy was designed by Bhutto to enhance national income and to extend more rights to the labour class which was suppressed through the privatization in the country during Ayub’s era. Some economic concessions and other facilities were also extended to the labour and working class under the new labour policy.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7668_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is an agro-based industry?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7668_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Agro-based industries are those industries which are run by the raw material produced from the agricultural sector. There are many examples of agro based industries like textile industry which is run by the cotton produced from the agriculture sector, floor mills are run by the wheat produced by the agricultural sector. Similarly rice husking mills and sugar mills are also run by the products produced from the agricultural sector.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7669_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is animal husbandry?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7669_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The scientific branch of agriculture concerned with the care and breeding of domestic animals and cattle such as sheep, goat, buffaloes and horses is called as animal husbandry. 
The proper breeding of the animals requires planning and care, and a lot of human effort.  The government is running a lot of projects for encouraging animal’s growth. Animal husbandry and colleges of research are established to breed and cure useful classes of animals. Department of livestock also provides support system for raising animals production both in government and private sector. In addition, military farms are also contributing a lot for the production and breeding of these animals. Animals are very important source of production of food items and they need a lot of care.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7666_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the definition of a Muslim in the constitution of Pakistan?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7666_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Through an amendment in 1974 the definition of a Muslim was inserted in the Constitution of 1973, which defines a person as a Muslim who believes in Tauheed or Oneness of Allah, and in the prophet hood of Hazrat Mohammad (P.B.U.H) as the last prophet of Allah. Before this no such provision existed in the 1956 and 1962 Constitutions.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7663_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Martial Law?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7663_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Martial law can be described as the military intervention in the democratic process by hook or crook. Most of the developing countries have been experiencing military rule in the national politics and the decision making process. Owing to several reasons, these developing countries could not evade military intervention in the political affairs. This practice resulted, perpetually into the apprehensions of total power. The reason behind this is the dearth of proper institutionalization. The trend of military involvement in the politics throughout the developing countries is recurrent, pervasive and rampant in nature. In the developing countries, main civilian institutions are very few and weak in nature, in addition some countries even lack civilian institutionalization. Therefore, in these countries, civilian control is loose and paves a way for the military intervention, and are referred as the “Praetorian States”  
Since the emergence of the state, military bureaucracy occupied a dominant place in Pakistan. This oligarchy has even been in the effective control of power politics. There are four levels of military intervention in politics, influence, blackmail, displacement and supplement. These levels of intervention are attained by various methods alone or in conjunction with one another.  The supplement of civil government can also take place through military take over with or without violence, commonly known as coup.
The state of Pakistan has experienced four martial laws since its creation. Military in Pakistan has always played a pivotal role and has remained the ultimate arbitrator in state affairs. It had remained the focus of the central power. It is obvious from the fact that more than half of the period since its birth, Pakistan had remained under the direct military control. Along with the direct control, military do have a significant part to play in the politics of the country even when it was out of the power. It is also said that Pak-India defense potential has made army in a commanding position over the civilian institutions and this phenomenon is known as “India Syndrome”. Parliamentary democracy and democratic institutions could not flourish in Pakistan due to the military interventions time and again.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7664_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are the Powers of the president?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7664_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Powers of the president are the powers that have been granted to the president under the constitution. In all the constitutions of Pakistan various presidential powers have been defined for the president. The 1962 Constitution was a presidential constitution where President was the focal point of political system having all the political legislative, executive and judicial powers and authorities.  He had executive and legislative powers because he was the part of the legislative process. Moreover, the cabinet was appointed by the president and was answerable to the president. He had the authority to remove a cabinet member anytime and other key appointments in the state were also made by the president. For example the appointment of Chief Justice and judges of the Supreme Court, services chief, chairman and the members of the Federal Public Service Commission (FPSC) and some other appointments were also made by the president through a proper procedure. 
President also had the powers to issue ordinances when the National Assembly was not in session. President also had emergency powers to declare state of emergency in case of unavoidable circumstance in the country.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7665_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is a federal system?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7665_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Federal System is a form of political system in which there is division of power between the centre and the provinces, a written constitution, supremacy of the judiciary and enough provincial autonomy is guaranteed to the constituting units of a federation. Division of powers between the centre and the provinces is an important characteristic of federal system. The Constitution of 1973 provided a federal system where federation of Pakistan has four provinces and federally administered areas. For division of powers between the centre and the provinces two lists of subjects are given: Federal list and Concurrent list. Federal list provides powers reserved for the federal government under which the federal government can legislate and make laws. 
The second is the concurrent list which is available to the federal government and the provinces as well. Under the concurrent list both parliament and the provincial assemblies can legislate but the federal laws have precedence over provincial laws. Enough provincial autonomy is guaranteed in the 1973 Constitution but the centre has some emergency and overriding powers over the provinces. The residuary powers were vested with the provinces and all the provinces are dependent on the centre for finances. In case of any dispute related to any subject between the centre and the provinces the decision of the federal government prevails. 
Provincial governors are appointed by the president on the advice of the Prime Minister who can impose governor rule if the provincial government cannot function properly in the province. The Constitution also provided an independent judiciary which plays an important role so far as the interpretation of the constitution is concerned.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7662_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What do you know about the One Unit Scheme (1955)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7662_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The most important constitutional issue for constitution making after independence was the issue of representation of various provinces in the legislature. The situation was that 56 percent of the country’s population was determined in only one province (East Pakistan). The remaining 44 percent of the population was spread in the 4 provinces of West Pakistan and several small states. If population had been regarded as the standard of representation, then the East Pakistan would have got a permanent majority in the assembly. 
The provinces and the states of West Pakistan were afraid of permanent domination of East Pakistan and such fears were not totally baseless. The Prime Minister Mohammad Ali Bogra presented a standard formula on 22 November 1954 to solve this issue of representation, in which the various units of West Pakistan were amalgamated into One Unit and representation was given to East and West Pakistan in legislature on the parity bases. The one unit bill was finally approved by the National Assembly of Pakistan on 14, October 1955.
The One Unit Scheme met with great resistance from the four provinces of the West Pakistan and the East Pakistan. It remained in effect until 1970, when General Yahya khan imposed Legal Framework Order (LFO) in which One Unit Scheme was abolished and the provincial status of the four provinces of West Pakistan was restored as of August, 1947.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7661_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the importance of Objectives Resolution(1949)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7661_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The Objectives Resolution is a basic and primary document of the constitutional history of Pakistan. It is a framework that provides mechanism to achieve goals for a better life of the people of Pakistan. Whenever we discuss history of constitution making even history of politics Objectives Resolution is very important. It’s important that it embraces centrality of Islam to polity sustaining their links with the pre-independence period and the post independence period. The All India Muslim League leaders were modernist Muslims not in favour of an orthodox religious state. Therefore, they selected the middle way abiding by the Islamic laws and the international democratic values. The Resolution remained ‘Preamble of all the constitutions due to its importance and during the period of General Zia-ul-Haq Objectives Resolution was incorporated in the constitution of Pakistan as the article 2-A.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7660_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What do you know about the Cripps Mission 1942?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7660_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Cripps Mission comprised of a set of proposals which were set up by the British government in March, 1942. These were slight improvements on the offer which was made to the Indian leaders in 1940. The Cripps Mission emphasized that ultimately
1.	India would be given a dominion status
2.	Indian constitutional body would frame the constitution that is the Indians would frame the new constitution.
3.	The princely states would also be represented in the assembly as well as in the future dominion system.
4.	The constitution would be acceptable to the British government provided certain conditions are met and one of these conditions was that any province not joining could retain its present position or these non acceding provinces could form their own unions.
5.	It also talked about the religious and racial minorities.
The Congress was very critical of the non acceding clause that certain provinces could stay out of that and the Congress was critical of that and it wanted responsible government to be introduced immediately. The Muslim League asked for two separate constituent assemblies, a separate constituent assembly for Pakistan. It argued that its objective is the establishment of Pakistan.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7615_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was chora chori incident?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7615_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In 1920 Non Cooperation Movement was launched by Gandhi, it was argued that this would be a peaceful and non violent movement. The Indians would demonstrate against the British in a peaceful manner even if the British used force against them, they would not respond. However, with the passage of time violence erupted during this non cooperation movement and there was an increase in violence day by day. The Chora chori Incident in Uttar Pradesh in February 1922 worsened the situation. Chora Chori was a small village in Uttar Pradesh and here what happened was the Congress activist attacked a police station as a part of agitation against the British. The Congress volunteers set a police station on fire; as a result about 21 policemen were burnt alive. There was other violence and due to this increase in violence Gandhi suddenly decided to call off the Non Cooperation movement.
Gandhi was shocked and confessed that he had committed “Himalayan Miscalculation” and called off the entire civil disobedience movement on 12 February, 1922; he was arrested and sentenced to six years imprisonment. As a result of this his colleagues resented at this step he had taken and were deeply disappointed.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7616_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Rowlett Act (1919)
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7616_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Rowlett Act was a black law introduced in India during the First World War. To the law, the government had the authority to persecute any Indian and the arrested had no facility of legal assistance and right to appeal as the ‘Lettres de Cachet’ in France before the French Revolution. Jinnah resigned from the central legislature as a protest against this black law. This was a law which the British government passed for arresting, detaining the people who were found involved in the criminal activities, but actually those were political activists. Those people could be punished swearly and without trial, both Hindus and the Muslims protested against this law and Jinnah was so much critical to this law. He delivered critical speeches in the legislative council and ultimately he resigned from his seat of the assembly in protest against this law, because he thought that this Act is a humiliating Act, which violates basic cannons of justice and fairplay.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7617_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Jallianwala Bagh Incident?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7617_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In April 1919, a number of Indians gathered in Jallianwala Bagh to protest against the brutal policies of the British government. General Dyer ordered fire to the troops, who were deployed there to suppress any protest, and they open fire on the protesting Indians. As a result 379 people died and thousands injured. It was the most tragic incident in the history of Subcontinent. It is also evident from this incident that the British always treated the Indians brutally and ruthlessly.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7618_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Aligarh Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7618_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Ali Garh movement was started by the Sir Syed Ahmad Khan and his colleagues for the educational and cultural uplift of the Muslims of British India. During this movement Sir Syed Ahmad Khan and his colleagues made great efforts, they established various schools, colleges, and universities to educate the Muslim community of the Subcontinent. A lot of books were also written by them to educate and upgrade the Muslims. Sir Syed Ahmad Khan also tried to create a better image of Muslims in front of British. He worked as a bridge between the Muslims and the British. He also tried to minimize the hatred and misunderstandings between the Muslims and the British. Many Muslim graduates of Ali Garh University participated in the freedom movement.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#7614_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Separate Electorate?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="7614_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Separate Electorate means to elect the representatives on the basis of religion and ethnicity. Moreover, the principle of Separate Electorate in the Subcontinent implied as demanded by the Muslims in 1906 in Simla Deputation keeping in view the diversity and the fact that there are different nations living in India. The Muslims consider themselves a separate identity and a separate nation. These things should be taken into account before introducing any system in India, because India has not been a homogeneous, amalgamated or monolithic political identity.
Therefore, the Muslims demanded that they should be given the right to elect their own representative. In this way, Muslims would be in a position to elect their own representatives that would represent them in the different institutions of India to project their demands. This demand of the Separate Electorate was the most significant demand of the Muslims at that time and it was accepted by the British in 1909 in Minto Morley Reforms and remained effective there until 1947.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1583_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">'AD.'and 'BC.' are acronyms of which words?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1583_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Anno Domini (Latin: "In the year of (Our) Lord"), abbreviated as AD or A.D., defines an epoch based on the traditionally reckoned year of the conception or birth of Jesus of Nazareth AD is also an abbreviation for ‘Christian Era’. 

Similarly, ‘Before Christ’ (is from the Ancient Greek "Christos" or "Anointed One", referring to Jesus), abbreviated as BC or B.C., is used in the English language to denote years before the start of this epoch.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1560_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Who was 'Jogendra Nath Mandal'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1560_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Jogendra Nath Mandal was the member of 1st Cabinet of Pakistan which was sworn on 15th August, 1947. He was the Minister of Law and Labour Ministry. He was basically leader of Scheduled Caste of Bengal and before partition he worked wholeheartedly with Muslim League in Bengal. That’s why even after partition he was included in Muslim League ministries. Later he resigned on 8th October 1950 to the Prime Minister Liaquat Ali Khan..
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1551_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is 'Interim Government'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1551_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Interim means an interval of time between one event, process, or period and another. Interim government means that government which fills the gap. When a working government is dismissed and there is a gap for election and appointment of new government then a temporary government thus formed is called Interim Government.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1548_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Had Chaudhry Rahmat Ali’s scheme met with success?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1548_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Prior to Chaudhry Rahmat Ali’s scheme it was an idealistic assumption that all the Muslim countries of the world should come together and become a single Islamic Ummah under a single government. These ideas were presented long before Chaudhry Rahmat Ali’s scheme. Chaudhry Rahmat Ali’s scheme was representative of his own understanding of the geopolitics of the area. It was an idealistic scheme similar to the scheme of Pan-Islamism but limited to South Asia. Usually ideals are there for motivation. If you achieve more than 50 percent of the ideal then you are successful. In the case of Chaudhry Rahmat Ali’s scheme more than 50 percent of the scheme was achieved in the form of Pakistan which shows that the scheme was a practical scheme and had met with success. Afghanistan had a separate status as an independent country and was not a part of British India. It remained independent after the Partition of the subcontinent.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1547_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are the impacts of Allama Iqbal’s Allahabad Address?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1547_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Impacts of Allama Iqbal’s Allahabad Address
The concept of Two Nation Theory was comprehensively explained and cleared in front of the Hindus, the Muslims and the British Government. For the first time the demand for a separate sovereign state was put forward and afterwards Muslims demanded not for separate electorate but for a separate homeland. He infused religious spirits which provided the Muslim with the hard needed guidance in every walk of life. Allama Iqbal’s address worked as guidance and provided outline to the Muslim League leadership for passing the famous Pakistan Resolution. Prior to Allahabad Address the Muslims were fighting for their rights with out knowing proper direction and destiny. Allama Iqbal’s Allahabad Address identified the destiny of the Muslims of the subcontinent and provided them with the direction to achieve that destiny. Allama Iqbal emphasized Islamic teachings in his address which were assimilated by the Muslim League in order to implement in a separate state of the Muslims. The Address was not specifically for the Muslims’ problems and their solution it also emphasized on solving the problems of all the communities of the subcontinent. Allama Iqbal’s Address made it clear to all the communities of the subcontinent that the Muslim leaders were sincere in solving their problems as well which evoked positive feeling about the Muslims leaders in them.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#2024_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the purpose of Allama Iqbal’s Allahabad Address?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="2024_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The purpose of Allama Iqbal’s Allahabad Address was to make a number of issues that were important for the Muslims of the subcontinent clear. Prominent among those issues were: Two Nation Theory, Provinces where the Muslims are in majority and their future status, political, social, religious problems etc. In addition to this Allama Iqbal wanted to divulge on all those issues in a manner that can win maximum support for the way the leaders of the All India Muslim League wanted to solve the problems of the subcontinent.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1133_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the role of OIC in resolving the conflicts afflicting the Muslims?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1133_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
OIC is trying to play an active role in order to resolve the conflicts that are afflicting the Muslims in different parts of the world. In a number of instances OIC has called for the emergency session of the Security Council of the United Nations and has presented resolutions condemning the wrongs that are being done to the Muslims. India, in the past, has tried to win membership of the OIC by claiming that it has 200 million Muslims population but the OIC refused to accept India as a member as India is brutally suppressing the Muslims in Kashmir. Indian atrocities in Kashmir, Israel atrocities in Palestine, Russian atrocities in Chechnya and other atrocities have been highly criticized by the OIC. In spite of all this OIC has failed to practically stop the commission of atrocities against the Muslims. There is a need to do a lot.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1132_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Was it a failure of democracy that led to imposition of Martial Law in 1958?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1132_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
It was not failure of democracy that led to imposition of Martial Law in Pakistan in 1958; it was basically failure of the leadership which resulted in the imposition of Martial Law. Inefficiency, corruption, intriguing of the politicians and some vested interests caused the democracy to fail in Pakistan. Systems never fail. Metaphorically speaking a good system is like a good car. Now car is good what is needed is good driver. Let’s suppose if the driver is not good and his intentions are out of the way then he will start driving the car in a wrong direction. It may cause accident and the car will not be able to approach its destination as it is driven in a wrong direction. If the driver drives the car in a right direction and with proper care and follows all the traffic rules the car will approach its destination easily and smoothly. Our leaders are the drivers of the system. If they are honest and they strive to take the system towards success then we can easily achieve success. If these leaders are corrupt and inefficient then we can never prosper and every system that will be introduced will meet the same ill fate as democracy has met in our country.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1130_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the importance of the Khilafat Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1130_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Although the Khilafat Movement failed to achieve its declared objectives, it carried a political awakening to large masses of Muslims. It was during the Khilafat days that representatives of Indian Muslims came into contact with eminent personages from other Muslim countries to save the semblance of unity in the world of Islam.
The Khilafat Movement was an asset for the struggle of Pakistan. It made clear to the Indian Muslims to trust neither the British nor the Hindus but to look to their own strengths for self-preservation. It was during the Khilafat Movement that the seed of new Muslim enthusiasm and leadership was sowed and it gave fruit in 1947 in the form of Pakistan.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1131_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the importance of Round Table Conferences for the Muslims?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1131_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Round Table Conferences have great importance for the Muslims of the subcontinent. During the course of the conferences, it became clear to the Muslims that who amongst them could articulate their demands effectively. It was Mr. Jinnah who effectively communicated the appropriate stance regarding the Muslim's interests and rights. On the communal issue, the Muslims won the sympathies of all the other communities of India against Hindus. The just stances taken on all the issues raised the Muslims’ stature in front of the British that the Muslims were sincere in solving the political and constitutional problem of British India. In the absence of Mr. Jinnah, the Muslims felt leaderless so it reinforced the leadership of Mr. Jinnah and then he was convinced to fill the gap of leadership. Moreover, the Muslims were able to convince the British regarding their interests and rights which later were accepted.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1542_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are the causes of the failure of the Khilafat Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1542_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The following are the causes of the failure of the Khilafat Movement:
1:- All the Khilafat leaders were arrested and put into jail.
2:- Gandhi called off his non-cooperation movement because of a violent incident of Chora Chauri.
3:- Grand National Assembly of Turkey under the leadership of Kamal Ataturk disbanded Khilafat.
4:- Highly oppressive policies and treatment meted out to the Khilafat workers by the British Government  
5:- The Khilafat Movement was rather an emotional movement than a rational movement. That was why it could not achieve its objectives and ended in smoke.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1543_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are the effects of the change of objectives, on the part of All India Muslim League, on the British Government?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1543_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Till 1911 the All India Muslim League was following the policy of loyalty to the British prescribed by the great reformer Sir Syed Ahmad Khan but after the ill-fated incident of the Annulment of Partition of Bengal, the leadership of the All India Muslim League decided to change the loyalties and started following the path of confrontation. It was a great change and this change culminated in the form of a change of objectives on the part of the League which was to achieve self-government suitable to India. It had a great effect, in the domain of politics, on the standing of the Muslims generally and of the League specifically. Prior to this, it was thought that the Muslims were working as puppets in the hands of the British and hurting the collective goal of self-government for India but the act of change of objectives by the League earned her great respect in the eyes of all the communities of India. Change of objectives resulted in reconciliation between the Congress and the League and finally, they agreed on the terms of the Lucknow Pact. After the Lucknow Pact, the Home Rule League was formed. As the British were engaged in the First World War this unity was another threat to the British control over its colonies. As a result, the famous policy announcement of 1917 was made which declared the progressive realization of responsible government in India as the final object of the British Government.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1544_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How did Allama Iqbal change from an Indian nationalist to a Muslim nationalist?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1544_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
At initial stage Dr Allama Iqbal was a nationalist by ideas and his poetry contained verses like Tarana-i-Hind. With the passage of time his thoughts voyaged from Indian nationalist to pan-Islamist and finally Muslim nationalist. He then started demanding separate state for the Muslims of the subcontinent on the premise that the Muslims of the subcontinent were a nation. His thoughts finally materialized in his Allahabad address where he said:
“I would like to see the Punjab, NWFP, Sind, Balochistan amalgamated into a single state as a self government within the British Empire or without”. To me this is the final destiny of the Muslims of at least N.W. India.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1545_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How did Sir Syed Ahmad Khan manage to fill the gap between the British and the Muslims?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1545_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
As the Muslims were showing great hatred against the British and English language and learning it so this hatred was creating misunderstanding between the Muslims and British. Due to tireless efforts of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan the Muslims started learning English language and started adopting the British culture and values which created a good image of the Muslims in the eyes of British government and the government, after this, was favorably oriented towards the Muslims. It was due to the efforts of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan in the field of education, politics and religion that the gap between the Muslims and the British generally and the British government particularly was shortened and both were able to understand each other. This understanding later resulted into a number of concessions for the Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1546_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Has the Khilafat Movement any similarities with the liberation struggle in Kashmir if we analyze it regarding the Hindu attitude?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1546_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In some aspects it can be related to the Kashmir struggle. The betrayal is the basic characteristic of the Hindus leadership. They betrayed the cause of the Muslims during the Khilafat Movement and now they are also betraying the cause of the Muslims in Kashmir. They promised to hold plebiscite in Kashmir in order to determine the wishes of the people of Kashmir but they have been reneging on their promises since they had occupied Kashmir by force. The Muslims should learn a lesson from the history and should no more trust the Hindus and their promises.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1784_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Poona Pact of 1932 and what is its importance?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1784_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The Communal Award was not popular with any Indian party. The Hindus refused to accept the awards and decided to launch a campaign against it. For them, it was not possible to accept the Untouchables as a minority. They organized the Allahabad Unity Conference in which they demanded the replacement of separate electorates by joint electorates. Many nationalist Muslims and Sikhs also participated in the conference. The Congress also rejected the Award in Toto. Gandhi protested against the declaration of the Untouchables as a minority and undertook a fast unto death. He also held meetings with the Untouchable leadership for the first time and try to convince them that they were very much part of the mainstream Hindu society. He managed to sign the Poona Pact with Dr. B. R. Ambedker, the leader of the Untouchables in which the Congress met many of the Untouchables' demands.
This Pact unearthed the real Hindu intentions that the Hindus were not ready to share power with even the suppressed classes of the Hindus and they wanted to concentrate power in the hands of highly privileged classes. Gandhi and the Congress were bent on enhancing their majority in the subcontinent in order to maintain their dominance. These facts helped the other communities of the subcontinent generally and the Muslims specifically to assess and anticipate the political maneuverings of Gandhi and Congress. After this, they were more cautious regarding their dealing with the Hindus.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1785_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the reason for the&nbsp;Shimla Deputation?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1785_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
When Lord Minto was appointed as the Viceroy on India in 1905, new reforms were indicated in which the elected principle would be extended. The anti-partition agitation had convinced the Muslims of the futility of expecting any fair-play from the Hindu majority. Therefore, to safeguard their interests, the Muslim leaders drew up a plan for separate electorates for their community, and presented it to the Viceroy Lord Minto at Simla, on October 1, 1906.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1540_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Who was Justice Amir Ali Syed?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1540_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Syed Ameer Ali traced his lineage through the eighth Imam, Ali Al-Raza, to the Holy Prophet (S. A. W.). One of his forefathers held office under Shah Abbas II of Persia. Another took part in Nadir Shah's invasion of India. After the plunder of Delhi, his forefathers decided to settle in the Sub-continent and started serving Muhammad Shah. Another of his forefathers fought against Marhattas in the third battle of Panipat. After the death of his grandfather, his father Saadat Ali Khan was brought up and educated by his maternal uncle. 
Saadat Ali Khan had five sons, Syed Ameer Ali being the youngest of them. He was born on April 6, 1849. His father, on the advice of some friendly British officers, made a break with the traditions and gave his sons an English education. Ameer Ali was educated at Hoogly College. He was a precocious child and learned Arabic, Persian, Arab philosophy, and history from his gifted father. He graduated in 1867 and became one of the first Muslim graduates in India. In 1868, he passed his MA in history and law, and in the same year proceeded to England on a government scholarship to pursue his higher studies. In London, he joined the Temple Inn and made contacts with the elite of the city. He imbibed the influence of contemporary liberalism. 
He returned to India in 1873 and resumed his legal practice at Calcutta High Court. The following year, he was elected as a Fellow of Calcutta University and was also appointed as a lecturer in Islamic Law at the Presidency College. He was one of the first leaders to clearly visualize that Muslims should organize themselves politically if they were to have an honored place in Indian public life. With this devotion, he established the Central National Muhammadan Association on April 12, 1877. He was associated with it for over 25 years and worked for the political advancement of the Muslims. In 1878, he was appointed as a member of the Bengal Legislative Council. He revisited England in 1880 for one year. 
In 1883, he was nominated to the membership of the Governor General Council. He became a professor of law at Calcutta University in 1881. In 1890 he was made a judge in the Calcutta High Court. He retired in 1904 and decided to settle down in England. This was a fateful decision in his career. Though, due to his influence in government circles, he contributed a lot to the Muslim community of India, while sitting in London, he was away from the main current of Muslim political life. Had he lived in India, he could have filled the gap in Muslim leadership created by the death of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan. 
He established the London Muslim League in 1908. This organization was an independent body and not a branch of the All India Muslim League. In 1909, he became the first Indian to sit as a Law Lord of the Privy Council. In 1910, he established the first mosque in London. His field of activities was now broadened and he stood for the Muslim welfare all over the world. He played an important role in securing separate electorates for the Muslims in South Asia and promoting the cause of the Khilafat Movement. 
He wrote a number of books on Islam and Islamic history. His most notable contributions are "The Spirit of Islam", "A Short History of the Saracens" and "Muhammadan Law". His book "Spirit of Islam", to some scholars, was the greatest single work on the liberal exposition of Islam. He died on August 4, 1928 in Sussex.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1536_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was wrong with the policies of the Mughals?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1536_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
First and important fault with the Mughals was that they could not institutionalize whatever good they did. Mughals had introduced a number of good policies but everything was dependent on one person. Policies used to be changed with the change of horse-man in the Mughal era. They could not introduce modern knowledge in the subcontinent and the people of the subcontinent lagged far behind in the field of technology and modern knowledge. Their focus in most of the cases was only on religious education. They did not make any effort to change the traditional economy totally dependent on agriculture to industrial economy. That was why European countries surpassed them in the field of technology and conquered the whole subcontinent. They were weak in diplomatic field as they kept on fighting wars even with the smaller states which were the part of their kingdom to suppress rebellion. They should have solved these problems diplomatically and politically and had saved considerable resources which they wasted on financing the wars.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1537_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are the bases of a modern Islamic state?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1537_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
A modern Islamic state should be based on pluralism and respect of diversity. The idea of the modern Islamic state is founded on principles that have been adopted by the contemporary Muslim as the foundations and the structure of his belief in a modern world. In a modern Islamic state a Muslim has endeavored to secure his pure Islamic identity while respecting the rights of minorities, seeking to espouse the culture of tolerance toward other cultures, respecting the supremacy of law, supporting cultural diversity, and applying equality and justice in all endeavors.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1538_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between a nation and a community?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1538_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Nation is a group of people who share common customs, origins, history, and language and are organized under a single usually independent government.
Community is a group of people living in the same locality and has common interests. Sense of nationalism is a prerequisite of a nation but this condition does not require for a community. The loyalty of a member of a community changes with the change of dwelling or area but the loyalty of member of nation does not changes. Wherever he is he will be ready to dedicate his efforts for his nation.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1539_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the role of leaders in the life of a nation?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1539_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Leaders have a decisive role in the life of a nation. Leaders are the drivers of a nation. If they drive a nation in a right direction then the nation will make progress and achieve prosperity but if leaders drive a nation in a wrong direction in order to satisfy their vested interests then the nation will be ruined.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1126_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why did Sir Syed Ahmad Khan start the Aligarh Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1126_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The purpose of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan’s Aligarh Movement was to create awareness among the Muslims about their separate identity, to warn them of the Hindu designs and plots hatched to subjugate the Muslims, and to make the British accept and treat the Muslims as a separate nation. As he was a great well-wisher of the Muslims, he thought the Aligarh Movement was a practical way to protect the Muslims' interests in the subcontinent. Given the conflicting interests, if Hindus and Muslims had been together after 1857, there would have been a civil war in the subcontinent and the resultant destruction and dejection. Giving them their separate status and separate domains to work for their prosperity was the only solution to the complicated situation of the subcontinent. This was the real purpose of the Aligarh Movement and Sir Syed Ahmad Khan effectively drove the Movement towards success.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1127_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What were the ideas of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan about religion?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1127_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sir Syed Ahmad Khan stood for a rational approach towards religion. He was not in the favour of blindly following the religious injunctions. He wanted the Muslims to develop thorough understanding of the religious injunctions and then follow these injunctions. He was of the view that man was not created for religion but religion was created for man. He argued that revealed truth could best be understood through reasons. The revelation of physical sciences could not be ignored in the understanding of religion. He was of the view that there could be no contradiction between the word of God (revealed truth) and work of God (the laws of physical science and phenomenon of nature). Same rational approach he used in explaining the creation of Angels (Malaika). He had considerable knowledge of the religion. Had he not been well-versed with knowledge of the religion he would not have been able to write a book on the life of the Last Prophet of God.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1128_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why did a number of Muslims keep them away from the Aligarh Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1128_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
There are a number of Muslims who were reluctant to follow the ideals of the Aligarh Movement. The underlying reason was the hatred against the British. This hatred did not allow them to learn English which was the language of the British who usurped power from the Muslims. Aligarh Movement advised the Muslim to learn English as with out learning English it was not possible to gain modern knowledge which was available in English. It was also not possible to communicate with the British with out learning English. The underlying purpose was to decrease the increasing distance between the rulers and the Muslims. On the other all the diehard Muslims were in favor of waging holy war (Jihad) against the British and then snatching back the reign of the subcontinent from them. Aligarh Movement was not in favor of waging war against the British but they wanted a peaceful solution of the problems of the subcontinent. Due to this difference of opinion a number of Muslims kept themselves away from Aligarh Movement.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1783_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why did the blame for the War of Independence of 1857 fall on the Muslims?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1783_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
As the Muslims were the rulers of the subcontinent so it was natural for the British to think that the Muslim would one day try to get back the reins of the rule of the subcontinent from the British. The role of the Muslim in the War of Independence of 1857 and the Hindus’ betrayal reinforced the above mention perception of the British. In the wake of the War the British in collusion with the Hindus started to persecute the Muslims. As the Hindus changed loyalties during the course of the War so this fact earned a good place for them in the eyes of the British. That was why the British heaped favours upon the Hindus and turned against the Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1781_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between the creation of Israel and the creation of Pakistan or what is the difference between the ideology of Pakistan and the ideology of Israel?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1781_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
There are a number of differences between the emergence of Israel and Pakistan. Pakistan was the result of a legitimate political struggle but Israel came into being through conspiracies, collusions, hidden plots, manipulations and by usurpation of the land and rights of the residents of the land of Palestine. The Muslims were in majority in all the areas which later became the parts of the state of Pakistan but today which is Israel even in that area Jews were in minority and local people were forced out of their homes and Jews were brought there from all over the world to create a numerical majority. The creation of Israel is the worst example of the usurpation of the rights of the hapless people and the creation of Pakistan is the best example of the legitimate political struggle for the rights of a group of people who takes inspiration from the same source which is Islam. Ideology of Pakistan was based on the just demands and legitimate rights of the peoples of the subcontinent but ideology of Israel was based on conspiracies, collusions, hidden plots, manipulations and on the idea of usurpation of the land and rights of the residents of the land of Palestine.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1750_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the Achhut Community?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1750_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Achhut Community is a term which refers to all the untouchables, lower class communities and Pariahs. They were highly suppressed and deprived peoples of the subcontinent. Brahmans and peoples of higher class had been exploiting them since long. It was generally perceived that they have lot of duties but no rights.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#30_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between a Prime Minister and a Chief Minister?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="30_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Prime Minister is head of the federal government and Chief Minister is head of the provincial government.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1494_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between ‘Partition of Bengal’ and ‘Division of Bengal’ and ‘Emergence of Bangladesh’?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1494_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Partition of Bengal occurred in 1905 under Lord Curzon, in which Bengal was divided in two provinces-East Bengal and West Bengal. This Partition was annulled in 1911 and the British government reunited Bengal province this incident known as ‘Annulment of Partition of Bengal’. 
Division of Bengal took place in 1947 under Radcliff Award when Bengal a large province of British India divided between Pakistan and India. East Bengal came to Pakistan and West Bengal went to India. 
Then in 1971 East Bengal was separated from Pakistan and achieved a statues of separate country named as ‘Bangladesh’ and it is called 'Emergence of Bangladesh'or 'Fall of Dhaka'.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1492_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between a ‘Theocratic state’ and a ‘Secular state’?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1492_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The system under which there is no state religion yet all religions and faiths enjoy equality of treatment. In the strict literal sense, secularism denotes a system that rejects belief in God, religion and future life. Theocracy is opposite to Secularism, a ‘religious State’ called theocratic state.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1488_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the outcome of the Gandhi-Jinnah Talks (1944)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1488_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In September 1944, Gandhi Jinnah talks were held at Jinnah’s residence at Bombay. Rajgopalacharia’s formula and the Lahore Resolution formed the basis of these talks. In these parleys Jinnah stressed on his famous Two-Nation Theory but Gandhi refused to accept Muslims as separate nation. Thus these talks remained fruitless.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1489_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was Quit India Movement (1942)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1489_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
After the failure of the Cripps Mission, India National Congress started ‘Quit India Movement’. In this Movement Congress was demanding that British should Quit India immediately and hand over powers to Indians. The British Government dealt with this Movement with iron hands. Thousands of Congress workers were killed arrested or detained. Muslim League remained aloof from this Movement.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1490_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was August Offer (1940)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1490_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In the start of Second World War Germany pushed the British troops out of the European mainland. At this critical juncture Great Britain needed the assistance of Indians to boost its War efforts. As a result the Viceroy of India Lord Linlithgow in August 1940 made a constitutional offer to the Indians in which he promised to expand the Executive Council of the Governor-General, to establish a War Advisory Council, to give constitutional safeguards to the minorities and to set up a constitution making body after the War. The Muslim League welcomed the offer but the Congress rejected it terming it insufficient and unsatisfactory.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1491_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between the Presidential system of government and the Parliamentary system of government?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1491_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In Presidential system the center of political power is the President but in the parliamentary system power rotates around the prime minister who is head of the government. In the parliamentary system President is only the ceremonial head of the state.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#576_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the Muhammadan Educational Conference?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="576_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Muhammadan Educational Conference was set up by Sir Ahmad Khan in 1866.Muhammadan Educational Conference held public meetings in various parts of the country. It established its sub-committees in all parts of the country. This Conference rendered valuable services in cultivating spirit of action and self-help among the Muslims. The meetings of this Conference discussed modern techniques for the development in the field of education and suggested ways and means for the adoption of modern techniques for the improvement of the educational standard. Some very eminent scholars and leaders were included in this conference who with their dedicated approach aroused hope, spirit and enthusiasm among their brethren. They were Nawab Muhsin-ul-Mulk, Nawab Viqar-ul-Mulk, Maulana Shibli and Maulana Hali who inspired the people with their spiritual, academic and political acumen and insight.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#824_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'Khutbat-i-Ahmadiya'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="824_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sir William Muir, a Christian writer, wrote a book with the title 'Life of Muhammad' in which he had made highly objectionable remarks about the Holy Prophet (PBUH).
In return, Sir Syed Ahmad Khan wrote 'Essays on the Life of Muhammad (Khutbat-i-Ahmadiya)' in which he gave proper answers to William Muir’s remarks in his book.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#823_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between a Viceroy and a Governor-General?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="823_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
A viceroy is typically a higher-ranking colonial official with more direct authority, often overseeing larger and more significant colonial territories. A governor-general holds a lower rank, governs smaller or less strategically significant territories, and may have less autonomy and direct authority. Both roles represent the monarch or colonial power in the respective territories.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#859_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">When did the British government create the North West Frontier Province?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="859_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In 1900, Lord Curzon created the North West Frontier Province in order to settle the constant battles that were going on there amongst the tough independent tribesmen. Before this NWFP was part of the Punjab Province. In 1900 it got the status of individual province in the British India.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#821_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'Tabyin-ul-Kalam'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="821_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sir Syed Ahmad Khan wrote ‘Tabyin-ul-Kalam’, in which he pointed out the similarities between Islam and Christianity. Due to lack of resources the work could not be completed, but it showed Sir Syed's commitment to improving relations between Islam and Christianity. This book was another effort on the part of Sir Syed, in the academic field, to create an atmosphere of good will between the British (who were Christian) and Indian Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#822_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'Tahdhib-ul-Aklaq'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="822_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sir Syed did not like conservative attitude of Muslims. He was worried about the social condition of Muslim and wanted the revival of their social life. He took many steps for betterment of the Muslims. For this purpose he published the magazine “Tahzib-ul-Akhlaq” This magazine outlined the ethical aspect of the Muslims life. Sir Syed criticized the conservative way of life of Muslims and advised them to adopt new trends in life. This magazine was written to teach the Muslims to adopt the true teaching of Islam and do not follow the social custom. For this purpose he opened a number of orphanage houses for Muslims children to save them from the influence of Christian missionaries.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#734_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the 'Doctrine of Lapse'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="734_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In 1848 Governor Dalhousie extended British control even further by applying the Doctrine of Lapse. According to this doctrine when a ruler dies without a natural heir the British would annex his land. This doctrine also stipulates that when a person dies without a natural heir his property would be acquired by the British Government.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#735_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'The Loyal Muhammadans of India'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="735_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In 1860 Sir Syed wrote 'The Loyal Mohammedans of India'. In this work he defended the Muslims from the British accusation that they were disloyal. He gave a detailed account of the loyal services rendered by the then Muslims and named various Muslims who had shown particular loyalty to the British. At the same time he called on the British to end their hostility towards the Muslim community.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#2099_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was difference between Viceroy and Sectary of State in British India?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="2099_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Viceroy was head of Indian affairs with in India appointed by British government and Sectary of State was head of Indian affairs in London.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#724_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the meaning of 'Dar-ul-Harb'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="724_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
This is meant an area where non-Muslims ruled.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#725_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Who was the founder of the 'Indian National Congress’ and who was the Indian Viceroy at that time?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="725_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
A former member of the Indian Civil Service, Allan Octavian Hume (commonly known as A. O. Hume), was founder of Congress. He formed Congress in 1885 and Lord Dufferin, was Viceroy of India at that time, fully supported him in his efforts.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1175_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">In which book did Sir Syed point out the similarities between Islam and Christianity?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1175_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In 'Tabyin-ul-Kalam' Sir Syed Ahmad Khan pointed out the similarities between Islam and Christianity. Due to lack of resources the work was not finished, but it showed Sir Syed's commitment to improve relations of British and Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1174_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was Jallianwala Bagh incident of 1919?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1174_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In April 1919, a number of Indians gathered in Jallianwala Bagh to protest against the brutal policies of the British government. General Dwyer ordered the troops, who were deployed there to suppress any protest, to open fire on the protesting Indians. As a result 379 people died and thousands injured. It was the most tragic incident in the history of the subcontinent. This incident is also evident to fact that the British treated the Indians brutally and ruthlessly.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#698_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the 'Day of Deliverance'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="698_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In protest against the policy of the British government over India regarding World War II, all the Congress Ministries resigned till October 22, 1939 and All India Muslim League decided to celebrate this development. So it was decided to celebrate December 22, 1939 as 'Day of Deliverance'. Deliverance was meant to be deliverance from the oppressive policies of the Congress Ministries.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#699_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between Parliamentary and Presidential system?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="699_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#700_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between Supreme Court &amp; High Court in terms of their powers?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="700_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Supreme Court is the highest court which accepts the appeals against the cases decided by the High Courts. The High Courts are at provincial level while the Supreme Court functions at the federal level.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#793_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">As British were against the Muslim so did they try to create any obstacle in the way of Aligarh Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="793_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The British Government was in favor of modernization amongst the Muslims and Aligarh Movement was striving to spread modern knowledge amongst the Muslims. The British did not create any obstacle in the way of Aligarh Movement which was working for educational and political development of the Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#605_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the impact of Aligarh movement on today’s Pakistan?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="605_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Majority of the leadership of Pakistan Movement was the product of Aligarh Movement. All India Muslim League was also created from one of the different platforms of Aligarh Movement. Emergence of Pakistan was the result of the efforts of the Aligarh Movement. Aligarh Movement is the best example for all of us today to learn how we can create dedicated and sincere leadership by the power of knowledge and how we can create a movement for the welfare of the Muslims of today.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#606_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Charismatic Leadership?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="606_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Charisma is a rare personal quality attributed to leaders who arouse fervent popular devotion and enthusiasm or personal magnetism or charm. Charismatic leader is a leader who possesses these traits and with the help of these qualities he inspires the masses to follow him and his program. This kind of leadership can bring revolutionary changes.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#607_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What are extra-constitutional means?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="607_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Extra-constitutional means are those means which cannot be justified under the prevalent constitution and are in violation of constitution.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#608_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is agitational politics and prejudice?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="608_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Agitational politics is a type of politics in which more and more protests and demonstrations are used to achieve political objectives. 
Prejudice means: 1: An adverse judgment or opinion formed beforehand or without knowledge or examination of the facts. 2: The act or state of holding unreasonable preconceived judgments or convictions. 3: Irrational suspicion or hatred of a particular group, race, or religion. 4: Detriment or injury caused to a person by the preconceived, unfavorable conviction of another or others.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#609_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">If British Government was in favor of Indian Muslims’ modernization, then how Hindu community came closer to the British Government rather than Muslims?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="609_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
After the War of Independence of 1857 the Hindus immediately adapted themselves to the changed rulers and environment. They started learning English and modern knowledge. On the other the Muslims refused to learn English and modern knowledge which was available in English. The blame of the War of Independence of 1857 fell on the Muslims. So it was natural for the British to co-opt the Hindus. The British thought that as the Muslims had been the rulers of the subcontinent prior to the British and those (Muslims) wanted to regain the control of the subcontinent and the War of Independence of 1857 was started by the Muslims to achieve that object. These were the reason which resulted into British-Hindu collusion. The British were of the opinion that the narrow-mindedness of the Muslims was the real cause of the problem so they if not supported but countenanced the Muslims thrust towards modernization.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#610_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was main cause of clash between Jinnah and Nehru on which Jinnah left the Congress?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="610_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The Congress had become explicitly a Hindu organization and had started working openly for the interests of the Hindus. This was the major reason that had convinced Mr. Jinnah to leave the Congress.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#611_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why and when did the British bestow the title of "Sir" upon the Sir Syed Ahmed Khan?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="611_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
It was the tradition of the British to award the title of 'Sir' upon the people with distinction. When Syed Ahmed Khan visited London in 1869-70, the title of ‘Sir’ was bestowed upon Syed Ahmed Khan, which entitled him to prefix his name with 'Sir'. Thence he became "Sir Syed Ahmed Khan".
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#612_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the difference between Aligarh Movement and Khilafat Movement?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="612_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Aligarh Movement and Khilafat Movement were different movements. Aligarh Movement was launched for the educational, political, social and religious uplift of the Muslims while Khilafat Movement was launched to protect the Ottoman Empire, Institution of Khilafat and the Muslim holy places.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#613_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Did Sir Syed Ahmed Khan have any enmity with Ulema?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="613_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sir Syed had no ill will or feelings against any Ulema, rather he wanted the Ulemas not to reject modern knowledge which was available in English because of their hatred against the British. He wanted them to work for the uplift of the Muslims by acquiring modern knowledge and also urged the Muslims to seek modern knowledge.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1142_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was SCIENTIFIC SOCIETY of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1142_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Scientific Society was an organization that was established by Sir Syed Ahmad Khan in Ghazipur. The purpose of this society was to create a scientific temperament among the Indians in general and the Muslims in particular and to make the Western knowledge available to Indians in their native languages. The society performed its job efficiently. Under this society the books of science, history and literature were translated into native languages because, according the concept of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan, it was impossible to spread the scientific knowledge among the Indians in general and the Muslims in particular till the scientific knowledge which was available in English would be made available to the Indians in their native languages.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1143_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How did Aligarh Movement play a scientific role?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1143_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Aligarh Movement played important role in scientific field by establishing different institutions which worked for the spread of scientific knowledge among the Indians. Prominent among those institutions was Scientific Society. The purpose of this society was to create a scientific temperament among the Indians in general and the Muslims in particular and to make the Western knowledge available to Indians in their native languages. The society performed its job efficiently. Under this society the books of science, history and literature were translated into native languages.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1186_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What weaknesses of Western culture were identified by Dr. Allama Iqbal?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1186_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
There were a number of weak aspects of the Western culture that were observed by Allama Iqbal i.e. separation of state and religion, territorial nationalism, deteriorating moral standards etc.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1140_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">How was Second Constituent Assembly formed?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1140_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The First Constituent Assembly of Pakistan was dissolved on October 24, 1954, by Governor General Malik Ghulam Muhammad. He called a Convention on May 10, 1955 for the purpose of electing members of Constituent Assembly. All its members were to be elected indirectly (by the provincial assemblies). In this way, the Second Constituent Assembly came into existence. The Second Constituent Assembly convened in 1955. It differed in composition from the First Constituent Assembly because of the notable reduction of Muslim League members and the presence of a United Front coalition from East Bengal.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1141_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What were the circumstances that led to the Lucknow Pact?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1141_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Important developments occurred during the first decade of the 20th century like annulment of the Partition of Bengal and Western aggression against Muslim countries, Balkan wars, Libya-Italy war, demolition of the mosque in Kanpur (1913), etc. weakened the Muslims’ faith in the British. This brought a major drift in the Muslim League’s policy. In 1913, the League changed its goals.
1: Self-government under the British Crown keeping in view the peculiar conditions in India
2: Good relations with other communities
3: Cooperation with any party working for similar goals
This change brought the ML and the Congress closer. In this way, the era of cooperation between Hindus and Muslims set in. In this regard, the role of the Quaid-i-Azam was highly noteworthy to bring the Congress and the Muslim League to the table. All these developments led to the conclusion of the Lucknow Pact in 1916.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#603_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why were the minorities of Pakistan not interested in s ‘Separate Electorates’?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="603_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
In Pakistan, the minorities were in a scattered position and it was too difficult for their representative to go to them, listen to their problems and finally solve their problems. They were only 3 percent of the total population. Moreover, there was no bias against them in the Muslim society. They had complete independence with regard to every sphere of life. The experience of separate electorates was not good for them. That was why they wanted to be part of the big majority.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#604_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Who was Sheikh Ahmad Sirhindi?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="604_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Sheikh Ahmad Sirhindi (Hazrat Mujadid Alf Sani) was a great saint and mystic of the Naqshbandi order. He challenged the might of Akbar, the great Mughal emperor, to re-establish the glory of Islam which had been greatly threatened by the anti-Islamic trends of Akbar.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1139_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'Indian Home Rule League'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1139_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
On April 23, 1916 Bal Gangadhar Tilak formed the Home Rule League in Bombay. Joseph Baptista became President and N.C. Kelkar was Secretary of Home Rule League which envisioned by Mrs. Besant.
Six months later Mrs. Annie Besant founded the league in Madras. Dr. Besant started the Home Rule League in India for obtaining the freedom of the country and reviving the country's glorious cultural heritage. The objective of both Home Rule League was to attain ‘self-government within the British Empire by all constitutional means’, and to educate public opinion for the same. They were Moderates and against the Liberal Party.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#855_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Who was Dr. Annie Besant?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="855_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Dr. Annie Besant was one of those foreigners who inspired the love of the country among Indians. In 1918, she declared ‘New India’ in her paper and said, "I love the Indian people as I love none other, and... My heart and my mind... have long been laid on the altar of the Motherland". Annie Besant, born of Irish parents in London on October 1, 1847, made India her home from November 1893. Dr. Besant started the Home Rule League in India for obtaining the freedom of the country and reviving the country's glorious cultural heritage. She started a paper called "New India”. She attended the session of the Indian National Congress in 1914 and presided over it in 1917. She died in 1933.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#591_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was Moplah Revolt?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="591_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Moplahs were the descendants of the Arab Muslims settled in the Sub-Continent even before the arrival of Muhammad Bin Qasim. In August 1921, they revolted against Hindu landlords at Malabar Coast, near Kalicut. Hindus feudal lords of that area with the collusion of the British managed to transfer large tracts of agricultural land to their name and this act antagonized the local Muslims who were poor peasants. These suffering poor peasant Muslims started an armed revolt against the local landlords and the government. The government resorted to repressive measures which resulted into deaths of thousands of Moplahs. It is called Moplah Revolt.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#469_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was 'Anjuman-i-Himayat-i-Islam'?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="469_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Some leading and sincere Muslim leaders like Maulana Qazi Hamid-ud-Din picked up the incentive in order to lessen the influence of the Hindu and Christian missionaries and decided to set up Anjuman-i-Himayat-i-Islam on September 24, 1884 in a mosque known as Masjid Bakan Khan inside Mochi Gate, Lahore, where nearly 250 Muslims decided to set up the Anjuman with the following aims;
To arrange for the religious and general education of Muslim
To propagate and defend Islam against the Christian missionaries and Hindu revivalists
To counter the propaganda against Islam through speeches and publications
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#536_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What kind of disagreement had Jinnah with Gandhi on the issue of Swaraj (Self-Rule)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="536_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
M. K. Gandhi wanted to introduce the Swaraj that was awarded by the British to its other colonies in which there were democratic governments (government by the majority). Whereas Quaid-e-Azam was opposed to such a setup and desired for self-rule which would be suitable to India and with due safeguards for the minorities. As the government by the majority meant ‘Hindu Raj’ in the Sub-continent. In fact, Quaid-e-Azam was against the Hindu-Raj and initiated the idea of Indians' rule.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#412_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was the Hindi-Urdu controversy?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="412_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
During the last days of the Muslim rule, Urdu emerged as the most common language of the north-western provinces of India. It was declared as a official language and all official records were written in this language. In 1867, some prominent Hindu leaders started a movement in Banaras in which they demanded the replacement of Urdu with Hindi, and the Persian script with the Devanagari script, as the court language in the north-western provinces. The reason for opposing Urdu was that the language was written in Persian script, which was similar to the Arabic script, and Arabic was the language of the Quran, which was the Holy Book of the Muslims. The movement grew quickly and within a few months spread throughout the Hindu population of the north-western provinces of India. The headquarters of this movement were in Allahabad. 
This situation provoked the Muslims to come out in order to protect the importance of the Urdu language. The opposition by the Hindus towards the Urdu language made it clear to the Muslims of the region that Hindus were not ready to tolerate the culture and traditions of the Muslims. 
The Urdu-Hindi controversy had a great effect on the life of Sir Syed Ahmad Khan. Before this event, he had been a great advocate of Hindu-Muslim unity and was of the opinion that the “two nations are like two eyes of the beautiful bride, India”. But this movement completely altered his point of view. He put forward the idea of Two-Nation Theory, predicting that the differences between the two groups would increase with the passage of time and the two communities would not join together in anything wholeheartedly.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1031_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What was Swaraj (self-rule)?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1031_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The term ‘Swaraj’ was meant that India should be ruled by Indians (natives)not by Britain. It was an objective to get rid of the Britain from Sub-continent and established a government led by the Indians. In other words, it meant complete independence for Sub-continent.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#411_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Can every political statement be described as an ideology?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="411_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The ideology is apolitical statement, but every political statement is not an ideology. Ideology may be explained as a cluster of ideas, beliefs and principles which has become deeply incorporated in the social consciousness of a group over time. In case of the Ideology of Pakistan, People believed in certain eternal spiritual ethical values which are enunciated from the Islam provided a base to demand a separate state and politicians raised the arguments in support of that idea which could be right or wrong. So, we can say that every political statement given by politicians cannot be described as an ideology. The political statement can be the argument in support of an ideology.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#853_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Islam believes in one nation (Ummah) then why Two Nation theory was propounded for the Muslims of the Sub-continent.
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="853_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
The religion of Islam defines its followers one Ummah (Nation). It doesn’t mean that all the Muslims of the world should come together and form one country. Islam believes in justice, peace, security and welfare of humanity. It exhorts its followers to struggle for the cause of justice, peace, security and welfare of humanity. No matter where they are, they should follow its commands and injunctions. Moreover, boundaries don’t matter in Islam. The more important beliefs are the complete submission to Allah, following in the footsteps of the Holy Prophet (PBUH) and continuous struggle for justice and welfare of humanity. Pakistan was created on the basis of Two Nation theory which states that Muslims differ from Hindus in terms of religious, cultural, social and daily life and that they must establish an independent Muslim state in which they can live freely their identities.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1023_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why RCD was replaced with ECO?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1023_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Pakistan, Iran and Turkey signed Regional Cooperation for Development (RCD) in July 1964. It worked for economic development till 1985. As it fell short of expectations and could not meet the goals set forth before it, so it was renamed as Economic Cooperation Organization (ECO). Later on, Afghanistan and five Central Asian Republics, Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan, Kyrgyzstan, Kazakhstan joined it. Now ECO is working for more cooperation among its members to enhance the development level of its members. Hope it will prove its worth and achieve the goal of development for its members.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#849_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">Why did British look upon Muslims as their enemies?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="849_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Muslims were the rulers of the Subcontinent so it was natural for the British to think that the Muslim would try to get back the reins of the rule of the Subcontinent from the British. The role of the Muslim in the War of Independence of 1857 and the Hindus’ betrayal reinforced the above mention perception of the British. In the wake of the War, the British in collusion with the Hindus started to persecute the Muslims. As the Hindus changed loyalties during the course of the War so this fact earned a good place for them in the eyes of the British. That was why the British heaped favors upon the Hindus and turned against the Muslims.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#851_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is foreign policy?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="851_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Foreign policy usually refers to the general principles by which a state governs its reaction to the international environment and its interaction with other states.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#1022_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is the Ideology of Pakistan?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="1022_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Ideology of Pakistan sought its roots from the religion of Islam. Basically, it means that Pakistan should be a state where the Muslims should have an opportunity to live according to their faith and creed based on the Islamic principles. They should have all the resources at their disposal to prosper and to enhance Islamic culture and civilization without any fear of being dominated by an unsympathetic Hindu majority.
<div class="m-accordion__item-head collapsed" role="tab" id="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-toggle="collapse" href="#382_Larget" aria-expanded="false">
<span class="m-accordion__item-title" style="word-break:break-word;">What is Two Nation Theory?
<div class="m-accordion__item-body collapse" id="382_Larget" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="m_accordion_2_item_1_head" data-parent="#m_accordion_2">
Two Nation Theory means that there were two major nations in British India. Both the nations were different and distinct from each other with regard to their culture, civilization, language and literature, art and architecture, names and nomenclature, sense of values and proportions, legal laws and moral codes, customs and calendars, history and tradition. In short, Muslims of the Sub-continent had their own distinct outlook on life and of life, so they would have their own separate homeland.
<!--end::Item-->
</div>
<!--end::Section-->
</div>
</div>